Register of the Enrique Bermúdez Varela papers, 1980-1990
Hoover Institution Archives
Enrique Bermúdez Varela papers
1977-1990
2011C43
Hoover Institution Archives
4 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (2.0 linear feet)
Reports, memoranda, clippings, and other printed matter relating to political conditions and civil war in Nicaragua.
Bermúdez Varela, Enrique, 1932-1991
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2011.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Enrique Bermúdez Varela was the founder, and for ten years the top official military commander, of the Fuerza Democrática Nicaragüense (FDN-Northern Front), also known as the contras. In that capacity, he and more overtly political leaders, (including Alfonso Robelo, Adolfo Calero, and Arturo Cruz,) met with United States president Ronald Reagan and other top officials. The contras' opposed the Frente Sandinista de Liberación Nacional (FSLN), or Sandinista, government.
Bermúdez graduated from the US Command and General Staff College at Fort Leavenworth and from the Inter-American Defense College in Washington. He served as chief of the Nicaraguan Delegation at the Inter-American Defense Board in Washington, DC in 1976 and as military attaché of the Nicaraguan Armed Forces at the Nicaraguan Embassy in Washington during the Nicaragua civil war. The civil war formally ended in 1987 with the Esquipulas II Peace Agreement, brokered by Costa Rican president Oscar Arias. In 1991 Bermúdez was lured back to Managua, where he was shot in a hotel parking lot with a small-caliber East German assassination pistol, one of several that had been delivered to Sandinista defense minister Humberto Ortega some years earlier.
Scope and Content of Collection
Reports, memoranda, clippings, and other printed matter relating to political conditions and civil war in Nicaragua.
Fuerza Democrática Nicaragüense.; Guerrillas--Nicaragua.; Nicaragua--Armed Forces.; Nicaragua--Foreign relations--United States.; Nicaragua--History--1979-1990.; Nicaragua--History--Revolution, 1979.; Nicaragua--Politics and government--1979-1990.; Nicaragua--Social conditions--1979-; Prensa (Managua, Nicaragua)
- Correspondence, 1982-1988 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- Printed matter, 1977-1990
  - Brochures, 1983-1988 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Clippings, 1980-1990 (Box-folder 1: 3-5)
  - Directiva Economica-Strategica, 1990 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Foro Democracia Para Nicaragua "Foundacion Romulo Gallegos" - Venezuela, 1989 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Newspapers, 1980-1990 (Oversize-box 5)
  - Periodicals, 1987-1989
    - Nicaragua Hoy, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Photocopied periodicals, 1977-1990 (Box-folder 1: 9-14, Box 2, Box 3, Box-folder 4: 1-2)
- Office files, 1980-1990
  - Memoranda, 1980-1990 (Box-folder 4: 3-4)
  - Reports, 1980-1990 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - ADREN, 1980-1990 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Comandante Franklin, 1989 (Box-folder 4: 7)
- Speeches and Writings, 1989-1990
  - Transcripts, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 4: 8)
- Legal Documents, 1988-1991
  - Briefs, 1988-1991 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Petition, 1988 (Box-folder 4: 10)
- Maps, 1988 (Box-folder 4: 11)